foreign
[Music]
there is a reason why there's a long
historical use of fruit purees as facial
masks and perhaps why Cleopatra was said
to bathe in sour milk
Alpha hydroxy acids also known as fruit
acids are natural acids found in Foods
they include citric acid from Citrus and
glycolic acid from sugarcane lactic acid
from fermented fruits malic acid from a
variety of fruits and tartaric acid from
grapes high strength concentrations are
used for chemical peels concentrations
over 40 can only be used by medical
doctors professionals and salons can
give more mild peels with 10 to 40 acid
Solutions but concentrations under 10
are sold over the counter as exfoliants
Alpha hydroxy acids are thought to work
by weakening cell to cell bonds to
hasten the shedding of dead cells off
the skin surface
three placebo-controlled studies of
over-the-counter strengths have been
published the first converted an eight
percent glycolic acid lotion to an eight
percent lactic acid lotion to a placebo
lotion applied daily on face and
forearms for 22 weeks both the acids
work similarly producing visible
improvements in facial photo damage and
more than 70 percent of the acid groups
versus only 40 of the placebo group all
the participants were advised to wear
protective clothing and regularly use
sunscreen which may explain the benefits
even in the placebo group
overall forearm photo damage and
soundness also improved significantly
the acid versus placebo groups about one
in three participants experienced
transient redness but only one out of 74
left the study due to facial irritation
the second trial found a five percent
glycolic acid lotion for three months
beat out Placebo and lessening skin
roughness and model discoloration on the
face and neck but failed to
significantly reduce wrinkle scores
the irony of alpha hydroxy acids is that
what they can help with past photo
damage they can make future damage worse
by increasing Skin photosensitivity So
taking precautions is recommended the
FDA recommends that all Alpha hydroxy
products be labeled with a prominent
warning sunburn alert this product may
increase your skin sensitivity to the
Sun and particularly the possibility of
sunburn use a sunscreen wear protective
clothing and limit sun exposure while
using this product and for a week
afterwards what about ascorbic acid also
known as Vitamin C if niacinamide works
by turning into antioxidants why not
just apply antioxidants directly
topical application can lead to vitamin
E levels in the skin 10 times what is
achieved by Oral dosing and vitamin C up
to 40 times higher at least in Mouse and
big skin respectively according to
review on topical anti-aging Skin Care
by a prominent Beverly Hills plastic
surgeon at a minimum patients should be
encouraged to use daily sunscreen
topical retinoid every night and a
topical antioxidant daily but there's
only one antioxidant that's been clearly
shown to work
despite its ubiquity and skin care
products there is no evidence to support
any role for topical vitamin E in skin
aging whether for wrinkles discoloration
or Texture the ones today on topical
CoQ10 also failed to work significantly
better than Placebo but there is one
type of vitamin C that has been shown to
help
skin biopsy studies show that the
topical application of a five percent
solution of l-ascorbic acid also known
as just ascorbic acid the type of
vitamin C found in food significantly
increases the expression of collagen in
human skin compared to Placebo
suggesting functional activity of the
skin cells is not maximal in
postmenopausal women and can be
increased a split face study involving
the application of three drops of a 10
l-ascorbic solution for three months
found significant improvements over the
placebo side of the face and finding
coarse wrinkles soundness and skin tone
or firmness
not knowing which side was which 16 out
of 19 84 percent of patients correctly
identified the vitamin C side as the one
showing Improvement
unfortunately l-ascorbic acid is
unstable in creams turning an unsightly
Brown when it oxidizes limiting its
shelf life so instead the Skin Care
industry uses more stable vitamin C
Esters or derivatives such as ascorpal
palmitate magnesium and scorable
phosphate ascorbic acid sulfate scorbo
steroid Etc
unfortunately there is no evidence that
these compounds have comparable effects
likely because they're poorly absorbed
and only minimally convert to the active
form the good news is that you can make
your own although vitamin C
concentration as low as three percent or
five percent have been shown to have
anti-wrinkle effects and split face or
split neck and arm studies 10 percent is
recommended the 10 solution used in this
study retails for a ridiculous
127 dollars per ounce you can make a DIY
solution more than 2 000 times cheaper
simply by buying L ascorbic acid in bulk
and mixing three grams into 30 grams of
water at a cost of about a nickel per
ounce you can mix it in an eye dropper
and drip four to five drops on the palm
of your hand and use your fingertips to
apply over your face neck and upper
chest daily just be careful to not get
any in your eyes
foreign